<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Feature SiLA2Version="1.1" FeatureVersion="1.0" MaturityLevel="Draft" Originator="org.silastandard" Category="core"
         xmlns="http://www.sila-standard.org"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.sila-standard.org https://gitlab.com/SiLA2/sila_base/raw/master/schema/FeatureDefinition.xsd">
  <Identifier>LabwareTransferController</Identifier>
  <DisplayName>Labware Transfer Controller</DisplayName>
  <Description>
    The Labware Transfer Controller feature provides commands to trigger the sub tasks of handing over a labware
    item, e.g. a microtiter plate, from one device to another in a standardized and generic way.

    For each transfer a defined sequence of commands has to be called on both involved devices, to ensure the proper
    synchronization of all necessary transfer actions without unwanted physical interferences and to optimize the
    transfer performance regarding the execution time. Using the generic commands labware transfers between any
    arbitrary labware handling devices can be controlled (a robot device has not necessarily be involved).

    A labware transfer is executed between a source and a destination device, where one of them is the active device
    (executing the actual handover actions) and the other one is the passive device.

    The sequence of issued commands is as follows:

    - Prior to the actual labware transfer a PrepareForOutput command is sent to the source device to execute all
    necessary actions to be ready to release a labware item (e.g. open a tray) and simultaneously a PrepareForInput
    command is sent to the destination device to execute all necessary actions to be ready to receive a labware
    item (e.g. position the robotic arm near the tray of the source device).
    Once, both devices have successfully finished their PrepareFor.. command execution, the next commands are
    issued.
    - If the source device is the active device it will receive a PutLabware command to execute all necessary
    actions to put the labware item to the destination device. After the transfer has been finished successfully
    the destination device receives a LabwareDelivered command, that triggers all actions to be done after
    the labware item has been transferred (e.g. close the opened tray).
    - If the destination device is the active device it will receive a GetLabware command to execute all necessary
    actions to get the labware from the source device (e.g. gripping the labware item). After that command has been
    finished successfully the source device receives a LabwareRemoved command, that triggers all actions to be done
    after the labware item has been transferred (e.g. close the opened tray).

    The command sequences for the involved devices with their respective roles have always to be as follows:
    - for an active source device:      PrepareForOutput - PutLabware.
    - for a passive source device:      PrepareForOutput - LabwareRemoved.
    - for an active destination device: PrepareForInput - GetLabware.
    - for a passive destination device: PrepareForInput - LabwareDelivered.
    If the commands issued by the client differ from the respective command sequences a InvalidCommandSequence error
    will be raised.

    To address the location, where a labware item can be handed over to or from other devices, every device must
    number its positions (handover positions). A robot usually has got at least one handover position for each other
    device it is interacting with, whereas the most none-transport devices will have only one handover position.
    In case of a position array (e.g. a rack) the position within the array is specified via the sub position of the
    handover position.

    To address the positions within a device (e.g. an incubator) where the transferred labware item has to be stored
    or is to be taken from, the internal position can be specified.

    All position information will be passed to the respective commands as index numbers.

    With the PrepareForInput command also information about the labware, like labware type or a unique labware
    identifier (e.g. a barcode), is transferred.

    The IntermediateActions parameter of the PutLabware and GetLabware command can be used to specify commands
    that have to be executed while a labware item is transferred to avoid unnecessary movements,
    e.g. if a robot has to get a plate from a just opened tray and a lid has to be put on the plate before it will
    be gripped, the lid handling actions have to be included in the GetLabware actions.
    The property AvailableIntermediateActions returns a list of commands that can be included in a PutLabware or
    GetLabware command.
  </Description>

  <Command>
    <Identifier>PrepareForInput</Identifier>
    <DisplayName>Prepare For Input</DisplayName>
    <Description>Put the device into a state where it is ready to accept new labware at the specified handover position.</Description>
    <Observable>Yes</Observable>

    <Parameter>
      <Identifier>HandoverPosition</Identifier>
      <DisplayName>Handover Position</DisplayName>
      <Description>Indicates the position where the labware will be handed over.</Description>
      <DataType>
        <DataTypeIdentifier>HandoverPosition</DataTypeIdentifier>
      </DataType>
    </Parameter>
    <Parameter>
      <Identifier>InternalPosition</Identifier>
      <DisplayName>Internal Position</DisplayName>
      <Description>Indicates the position where the labware will stored at inside the device, e.g. a storage position within an incubator.</Description>
      <DataType>
        <DataTypeIdentifier>PositionIndex</DataTypeIdentifier>
      </DataType>
    </Parameter>
    <Parameter>
      <Identifier>LabwareType</Identifier>
      <DisplayName>Labware Type</DisplayName>
      <Description>Specifies the type of the labware that will be handed over to transfer information about the labware that the device might need to access it correctly.</Description>
      <DataType>
        <Basic>String</Basic>
      </DataType>
    </Parameter>
    <Parameter>
      <Identifier>LabwareUniqueID</Identifier>
      <DisplayName>Labware Unique ID</DisplayName>
      <Description>The labwareUniqueID represents the unique identification of a labware in the controlling system. It is assigned by the system and stays the same for the whole process.</Description>
      <DataType>
        <Basic>String</Basic>
      </DataType>
    </Parameter>

    <DefinedExecutionErrors>
      <Identifier>InvalidCommandSequence</Identifier>
    </DefinedExecutionErrors>
  </Command>

  <Command>
    <Identifier>PrepareForOutput</Identifier>
    <DisplayName>Prepare For Output</DisplayName>
    <Description>Put the device into a state where it is ready to release the labware at the specified handover position.</Description>
    <Observable>Yes</Observable>

    <Parameter>
      <Identifier>HandoverPosition</Identifier>
      <DisplayName>Handover Position</DisplayName>
      <Description>Indicates the position where the labware will be handed over.</Description>
      <DataType>
        <DataTypeIdentifier>HandoverPosition</DataTypeIdentifier>
      </DataType>
    </Parameter>
    <Parameter>
      <Identifier>InternalPosition</Identifier>
      <DisplayName>Internal Position</DisplayName>
      <Description>Indicates the position where the labware will be retrieved from inside the device, e.g. a storage position within an incubator.</Description>
      <DataType>
        <DataTypeIdentifier>PositionIndex</DataTypeIdentifier>
      </DataType>
    </Parameter>

    <DefinedExecutionErrors>
      <Identifier>InvalidCommandSequence</Identifier>
    </DefinedExecutionErrors>
  </Command>

  <Command>
    <Identifier>PutLabware</Identifier>
    <DisplayName>Put Labware</DisplayName>
    <Description>Place the currently processed labware item at the specified handover position (sent to the active source device after a "PrepareForOutput" command).</Description>
    <Observable>Yes</Observable>

    <Parameter>
      <Identifier>HandoverPosition</Identifier>
      <DisplayName>Handover Position</DisplayName>
      <Description>Indicates the position where the labware will be moved to.</Description>
      <DataType>
        <DataTypeIdentifier>HandoverPosition</DataTypeIdentifier>
      </DataType>
    </Parameter>
    <Parameter>
      <Identifier>LabwareType</Identifier>
      <DisplayName>Labware Type</DisplayName>
      <Description>Specifies the type of the labware that will be handed over to transfer information about the labware that the device might need to access it correctly.</Description>
      <DataType>
        <Basic>String</Basic>
      </DataType>
    </Parameter>
    <Parameter>
      <Identifier>IntermediateActions</Identifier>
      <DisplayName>Intermediate Actions</DisplayName>
      <Description>Specifies one ore more commands that have to be executed within the command sequence (e.g. removing a lid). Each entry must be one of the commands returned by the AvailableIntermediateCommandExecutions property.</Description>
      <DataType>
        <List>
          <DataType>
            <Basic>String</Basic>
          </DataType>
        </List>
      </DataType>
    </Parameter>

    <DefinedExecutionErrors>
      <Identifier>InvalidCommandSequence</Identifier>
      <Identifier>LabwareNotPlaced</Identifier>
    </DefinedExecutionErrors>
  </Command>

  <Command>
    <Identifier>GetLabware</Identifier>
    <DisplayName>Get Labware</DisplayName>
    <Description>Retrieve a labware item from the specified handover position (sent to the active destination device after a "PrepareForInput" command).</Description>
    <Observable>Yes</Observable>

    <Parameter>
      <Identifier>HandoverPosition</Identifier>
      <DisplayName>Handover Position</DisplayName>
      <Description>Indicates the position where the labware will be retrieved from.</Description>
      <DataType>
        <DataTypeIdentifier>HandoverPosition</DataTypeIdentifier>
      </DataType>
    </Parameter>
    <Parameter>
      <Identifier>LabwareType</Identifier>
      <DisplayName>Labware Type</DisplayName>
      <Description>Specifies the type of the labware that will be handed over to transfer information about the labware that the device might need to access it correctly.</Description>
      <DataType>
        <Basic>String</Basic>
      </DataType>
    </Parameter>
    <Parameter>
      <Identifier>IntermediateActions</Identifier>
      <DisplayName>Intermediate Actions</DisplayName>
      <Description>Specifies one ore more commands that have to be executed within the command sequence (e.g. removing a lid). Each entry must be one of the commands returned by the AvailableIntermediateCommandExecutions property.</Description>
      <DataType>
        <List>
          <DataType>
            <Basic>String</Basic>
          </DataType>
        </List>
      </DataType>
    </Parameter>

    <DefinedExecutionErrors>
      <Identifier>InvalidCommandSequence</Identifier>
      <Identifier>LabwareNotPicked</Identifier>
    </DefinedExecutionErrors>
  </Command>

  <Command>
    <Identifier>LabwareDelivered</Identifier>
    <DisplayName>Labware Delivered</DisplayName>
    <Description>Notifies the passive destination device of a labware item that has been transferred to it (sent after a "PrepareForInput" command).</Description>
    <Observable>Yes</Observable>

    <Parameter>
      <Identifier>HandoverPosition</Identifier>
      <DisplayName>Handover Position</DisplayName>
      <Description>Indicates the position the labware item has been delivered to.</Description>
      <DataType>
        <DataTypeIdentifier>HandoverPosition</DataTypeIdentifier>
      </DataType>
    </Parameter>

    <DefinedExecutionErrors>
      <Identifier>InvalidCommandSequence</Identifier>
    </DefinedExecutionErrors>
  </Command>

  <Command>
    <Identifier>LabwareRemoved</Identifier>
    <DisplayName>Labware Removed</DisplayName>
    <Description>Notifies the passive source device of a labware item that has been removed from it (sent after a "PrepareForOutput" command).</Description>
    <Observable>Yes</Observable>

    <Parameter>
      <Identifier>HandoverPosition</Identifier>
      <DisplayName>Handover Position</DisplayName>
      <Description>Indicates the position the labware has been removed from.</Description>
      <DataType>
        <DataTypeIdentifier>HandoverPosition</DataTypeIdentifier>
      </DataType>
    </Parameter>

    <DefinedExecutionErrors>
      <Identifier>InvalidCommandSequence</Identifier>
    </DefinedExecutionErrors>
  </Command>

  <Property>
    <Identifier>AvailableIntermediateActions</Identifier>
    <DisplayName>Available Intermediate Actions</DisplayName>
    <Description>Returns all commands that can be be executed within a PutLabware or GetLabware command execution.</Description>
    <Observable>No</Observable>
    <DataType>
      <List>
        <DataType>
          <Constrained>
            <DataType>
              <Basic>String</Basic>
            </DataType>
            <Constraints>
              <FullyQualifiedIdentifier>CommandIdentifier</FullyQualifiedIdentifier>
            </Constraints>
          </Constrained>
        </DataType>
      </List>
    </DataType>
  </Property>

  <DataTypeDefinition>
    <Identifier>HandoverPosition</Identifier>
    <DisplayName>Handover Position</DisplayName>
    <Description>Specifies one of the possible positions of a device where labware items can be handed over. Can contain a sub position, e.g. for specifying a position in a rack.</Description>
    <DataType>
      <Structure>
        <Element>
          <Identifier>Position</Identifier>
          <DisplayName>Position</DisplayName>
          <Description>The index of the general handover position, if more then one is available (else 1).</Description>
          <DataType>
            <DataTypeIdentifier>PositionIndex</DataTypeIdentifier>
          </DataType>
        </Element>
        <Element>
          <Identifier>SubPosition</Identifier>
          <DisplayName>Sub Position</DisplayName>
          <Description>The index of a sub position within a handover position, e.g. for a rack.</Description>
          <DataType>
            <DataTypeIdentifier>PositionIndex</DataTypeIdentifier>
          </DataType>
        </Element>
      </Structure>
    </DataType>
  </DataTypeDefinition>

  <DataTypeDefinition>
    <Identifier>PositionIndex</Identifier>
    <DisplayName>Position Index</DisplayName>
    <Description>Specifies a position via an index number, starting with 1.</Description>
    <DataType>
      <Constrained>
        <DataType>
          <Basic>Integer</Basic>
        </DataType>
        <Constraints>
          <MinimalInclusive>1</MinimalInclusive>
        </Constraints>
      </Constrained>
    </DataType>
  </DataTypeDefinition>

  <DefinedExecutionError>
    <Identifier>InvalidCommandSequence</Identifier>
    <DisplayName>Invalid Command Sequence</DisplayName>
    <Description>The issued command does not follow the sequence of commands for the device according to its role in the labware transfer.</Description>
  </DefinedExecutionError>

  <DefinedExecutionError>
    <Identifier>LabwareNotPicked</Identifier>
    <DisplayName>Labware Not Picked</DisplayName>
    <Description>Picking up the labware item from the source device failed.</Description>
  </DefinedExecutionError>

  <DefinedExecutionError>
    <Identifier>LabwareNotPlaced</Identifier>
    <DisplayName>Labware Not Placed</DisplayName>
    <Description>Placing the labware item at the destination device failed.</Description>
  </DefinedExecutionError>

</Feature>